 {"Professional Ethics":[
    {
   "id": "1",
   "question": "One of the following is not a necessary condition to be fulfilled by aspirants to the Nigerian Bar",
   "options": {
    "a": "Success at Law School Portfolio Assessment",
    "b": "Nigerian Citizenship",
    "c": "Good Conduct",
    "d": "Success at Bar Part II Examinations "
   },
   "answer": "Nigerian Citizenship",
   "reason": "Decree No.9 of 1922 allows for non-Nigerians to be called to the Nigerian Bar"
  },
    {
   "id": "2",
   "question": "All of the following are incorrect about the processing fee required of applicants for the rank of Senior Advocate of Nigeria except:",
   "options": {
    "a": "The sum is ₦1,000,000",
    "b": "It is non-refundable",
    "c": "The sum is ₦200,000",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "The sum is ₦1,000,000",
   "reason": "Every Applicant for the rank of SAN shall pay a non-refundable processing fee in the sum of ₦1,000,000 or such amount as may be fixed by the LPPC. Section 9(3) of the Guidelines for the Conferment of the Rank of SAN 2018 (It has been amended)."
  },
    {
   "id": "3",
   "question": "A lawyer who is in active legal practice is prohibited from being:",
   "options": {
    "a": "The Managing Director of a company",
    "b": "A shareholder of a company",
    "c": "The Chairman of a company",
    "d": "A non-executive director of a company"
   },
   "answer": "The Managing Director of a company",
   "reason": "Managing Director of a company is an executive officer of the company, but the Chairman is a non- executive officer. Rule 7(3), RPC"
  },
    {
   "id": "4",
   "question": "To enjoy the exclusive rights of legal practitioners in Nigeria, a lawyer must have to do all the following except",
   "options": {
    "a": "Payment of practising fees promptly",
    "b": "The appropriate use of seal and stamp",
    "c": "Participating in mandatory continuing legal education",
    "d": "Contesting for executive positions of the NBA"
   },
   "answer": "Contesting for executive positions of the NBA",
   "reason": "Rule 10 makes stamp and seal compulsory, Rule 9 does the same for practising fee and Rule 11 does the same for mandatory continuing legal education, prescribing hours expected of lawyers"
  },
    {
   "id": "5",
   "question": "Tony, a 10 year old girl, was raped by two thugs on her way home from school. She was brutally injured and left to die, but was miraculously rushed to the Hospital by passers-by and she survived. Furious and determined to end the lives of the two thugs, Carlee Jackson, the father of Tony, contacted Jimoh Esq and told him of his intention to kill the thugs and should be be charged to court, Jimoh would defend him. Jimoh advised him to go ahead saying if he found himself in similar situation, he would have killed the thugs a long time ago. Which professional duty has Jimoh Esq breached from the scenario?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Duty to advise his client within the bounds of the law",
    "b": "Duly to prevent the commission of a crime",
    "c": "Duty to uphold the rule of law",
    "d": "All of the above "
   },
   "answer": "All of the above ",
   "reason": "See Rule 1 and 15 of the RPC 2023"
  },
    {
   "id": "6",
   "question": "A counsel does not owe any duty to the",
   "options": {
    "a": "Client",
    "b": "State",
    "c": "Court",
    "d": "None of the Above"
   },
   "answer": "None of the Above",
   "reason": "Rules 14 - 25 provides for duties to client, Rules 26 - 29 provides for duties to other lawyers, Rules 30 - 38 provides for duties to the court"
  },
    {
   "id": "7",
   "question": "What does the Rule 39 provides for?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Dedication and devotion to the cause of the client",
    "b": "Withdrawal from employment",
    "c": "Instigating litigation",
    "d": "Advertising and soliciting"
   },
   "answer": "Advertising and soliciting",
   "reason": "A lawyer can advertise to an extent but cannot solicit."
  },
    {
   "id": "8",
   "question": "All except one are members of the National Judicial Council",
   "options": {
    "a": "Chief Justice of Nigeria",
    "b": "Attorney General of the Federation",
    "c": "Next most senior Justice of the Supreme Court",
    "d": "President of the Court of Appeal"
   },
   "answer": "Attorney General of the Federation",
   "reason": "The AGF is not a member of the NJC. See the composition of the NJC, Third Schedule, CFRN"
  },
    {
   "id": "9",
   "question": "The total membership of the National Judicial Council according to the Constitution is",
   "options": {
    "a": "24",
    "b": "23",
    "c": "25",
    "d": "26"
   },
   "answer": "24",
   "reason": " See Third Schedule, CFRN as amended."
  },
    {
   "id": "10",
   "question": "The Legal Practitioners Disciplinary Committee has decided to try Franklin for the professional offence(s) committed. Which of the following constitutes proper parties before the Committee?",
   "options": {
    "a": "NBA v Franklin",
    "b": "BOB v Franklin",
    "c": "LPDC v Franklin",
    "d": "Registered Trustees of NBA v Franklin"
   },
   "answer": "Registered Trustees of NBA v Franklin",
   "reason": "See section 11 of the Legal Practitioners Act 1975"
  },
    {
   "id": "11",
   "question": "The Legal Practitioners Disciplinary Committee Rules was made by",
   "options": {
    "a": "The Attorney General of the Federation",
    "b": "The President of the Court of Appeal",
    "c": "The Chief Justice of Nigeria",
    "d": "The National Assembly"
   },
   "answer": "The Chief Justice of Nigeria",
   "reason": "Section 10(7) LPA."
  },
    {
   "id": "12",
   "question": "The standard of proof in contempt in facie curiae is",
   "options": {
    "a": "Balance of probability",
    "b": "Beyond reasonable doubt",
    "c": "Proof to the satisfaction of the Court",
    "d": "Clear and convincing evidence"
   },
   "answer": "Beyond reasonable doubt",
   "reason": "Proof of contempt, whether civil or criminal, is beyond reasonable doubt. This is because the outcome of contempt is penal in nature."
  },
    {
   "id": "13",
   "question": "In legal drafting, how many types of paragraphing techniques do we have?",
   "options": {
    "a": "2",
    "b": "3",
    "c": "4",
    "d": "5"
   },
   "answer": "2",
   "reason": "There are two paragraphing techniques: two layered paragraph and three layered paragraph"
  },
    {
   "id": "14",
   "question": "You were an extern in the Legal Drafting Department of the Ministry of Justice of Lagos State. The Director has asked you what part of a legislation broadly captures main themes of the legislation?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Short Title",
    "b": "Long Title",
    "c": "Preamble",
    "d": "Commencement Clause"
   },
   "answer": "Long Title",
   "reason": "The Long title captures the main theme of the legislation"
  },
    {
   "id": "15",
   "question": "The doctrine of construing documents e.g. contracts that are ambiguous against the maker is termed",
   "options": {
    "a": "Utres magisvale at quam pereat",
    "b": "Ejusdem generis",
    "c": "Contra preferentem ",
    "d": "Generalibuss pecialiaderogant"
   },
   "answer": "Contra preferentem ",
   "reason": "The contra proferentem rule means that the words of a written document, usually an exclusion clause in a contract, are construed more forcibly against the party using them."
  },
    {
   "id": "16",
   "question": "The rule relating to ordering witnesses out of court and hearing does not apply to:",
   "options": {
    "a": "Expert witnesses",
    "b": "Claimant",
    "c": "Subpoenaed witnesses",
    "d": "Eye witnesses"
   },
   "answer": "Claimant",
   "reason": "sec. 212 of Evidence Act"
  },
    {
   "id": "17",
   "question": "The statutory period for keeping closed files is",
   "options": {
    "a": "6 years",
    "b": "3 years",
    "c": "4 years",
    "d": "None"
   },
   "answer": "None",
   "reason": "There is no statutory period or limit within which closed files are to be kept."
  },
    {
   "id": "18",
   "question": "The following are ethical issues in client interview and counselling except:",
   "options": {
    "a": "Advising the client within the bound of the law",
    "b": "Preserving confidential information",
    "c": "Assuring the client of the success of his claim",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "Assuring the client of the success of his claim",
   "reason": "You can't assure the client of success but you can brief him of the relative strengths and weaknesses of the case"
  },
    {
   "id": "19",
   "question": "A lawyer is allowed to make reasonable and permissible advertisements on all but one of the following",
   "options": {
    "a": "Fliers and billboards",
    "b": "Signs and notices",
    "c": "Books and articles",
    "d": "Notepapers and envelopes "
   },
   "answer": "Fliers and billboards",
   "reason": "see Rule 39 RPC 2023"
  },
    {
   "id": "20",
   "question": "Which of the following ADR mechanisms is regulated by the law?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Arbitration",
    "b": "Mediation",
    "c": "Conciliation",
    "d": "A and C"
   },
   "answer": "A and C",
   "reason": "Arbitration and Conciliation Act"
  },
  {
   "id": "21",
   "question": "Which of the following is a disciplinary measure that can be meted out to erring judicial officers?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Recommendation for dismissal",
    "b": "Demotion to a lower court",
    "c": "Non promotion to a higher court for a period of 10 years",
    "d": "Non promotion to a higher court for a period of 5 years"
   },
   "answer": "Recommendation for dismissal",
   "reason": "The disciplinary measures against a judicial officer are removal and suspension. It must be noted that the NJC does not have the power of removal, but can only recommend such"
  },
  {
   "id": "22",
   "question": "A complaint against a Judicial Officer can be addressed to:",
   "options": {
    "a": "The Chairman NJC",
    "b": "Chief Justice of Nigeria",
    "c": "A and B",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "A and B",
   "reason": "The CJN is the Chairman of the NJC. see section 153 CFRN"
  },
  {
   "id": "23",
   "question": "The Chief Justice of Nigeria is the Chairman of which of the following regulatory bodies:",
   "options": {
    "a": "The National Judicial Council",
    "b": "The Legal Practitioners Privileges Committee",
    "c": "Legal Practitioner Disciplinary Committe",
    "d": "A and B"
   },
   "answer": "A and B",
   "reason": "The CJN is the Chairman of the NJC as well as the LPPC. See Sec. 5(3), LPA and Third Schedule to the 1999 Constitution as amended."
  },
  {
   "id": "24",
   "question": "The following restrictions apply to Senior Advocates of Nigeria except:",
   "options": {
    "a": "They shall not draft any instrument where the charge is below ₦400.",
    "b": "They shall not handle any pro bono case personally, but shall give it to his junior",
    "c": "They shall not appear in any criminal case alone without a junior counsel",
    "d": "B and C"
   },
   "answer": "B and C",
   "reason": "There is nothing which prevents SANs from handling probono cases themselves. Likewise, they can appear alone without any junior in a criminal case, not civil case."
  },
  {
   "id": "25",
   "question": "A person who is not a lawyer can be appointed as a Judicial Officer in which of the following courts",
   "options": {
    "a": "Customary Court of Appeal",
    "b": "Sharia Court of Appeal",
    "c": "A and B",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "A and B",
   "reason": "a non-lawyer is qualified for appointment as judge of the Customary Court of Appeal or Kadi of the Sharia Court of Appeal. See. Sec. 261 and 266, CFRN."
  },
  {
   "id": "26",
   "question": "The rules guiding the conduct of dinner for candidates of the Nigerian Bar were prescribed by:",
   "options": {
    "a": "The Council of Legal Education",
    "b": "The Body of Benchers",
    "c": "Director General of Nigerian Law School",
    "d": "Nigerian Bar Association"
   },
   "answer": "The Body of Benchers",
   "reason": "One of the functions of the BOB is the prescription of dining rules."
  },
  {
   "id": "27",
   "question": "One of the following is not an exclusive right of legal practitioners:",
   "options": {
    "a": "Appointment as notary public",
    "b": "Statutory declaration of compliance",
    "c": "Registration of business name",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "Registration of business name",
   "reason": "Registration of business names and even companies are not part of the exclusive rights of legal practitioners. Statutory declaration is still an exclusive right of a legal practitioner although it is no longer a necessity in registering a company as a statement of compliance by an agent will suffice. see section 40(3) CAMA 2020."
  },
  {
   "id": "28",
   "question": "All but one of the following are not judicial officers:",
   "options": {
    "a": "Kadis of the Sharia Court of Appeal",
    "b": "Judges of customary courts",
    "c": "Chief Magistrates of various courts",
    "d": "Judges of Area Courts"
   },
   "answer": "Kadis of the Sharia Court of Appeal",
   "reason": "Customary Courts, Area Courts and Magistrates Courts are not superior courts, thus, judges and magistrates of these courts are not regarded as judicial officers. Sec.318, CFRN."
  },
  {
   "id": "29",
   "question": "One of the following is incorrect",
   "options": {
    "a": "A lawyer who practices at the bar can engage in any other profession if permitted by the Bar council",
    "b": "A director of a registered company shall not appear as an advocate in court or in a judicial tribunal for his company",
    "c": "A retired judicial officer cannot represent himself in court",
    "d": "A lawyer who has not paid his practicing fee will be denied right of audience."
   },
   "answer": "A retired judicial officer cannot represent himself in court",
   "reason": "See; Atake v Afejuku, Rule 6, RPC."
  },
  {
   "id": "30",
   "question": "During the recently concluded portfolio assessment at the Nigerian Law School, Mary, a student, gave an account in her log book of witnessing Mr. Okeke Dabo, a nonlawyer prosecuting his personal matter in court. Which of the following is a correct statement in respect of Mr. Okeke Dabo?",
   "options": {
    "a": "The RPC prohibits him from prosecuting any case in court unless he is called to bar",
    "b": "He may prosecute his personal case in Court",
    "c": "He may prosecute his personal case in court provided he does not cite legal authorities and use legal jargon",
    "d": "He may prosecute his matter only at an inferior court"
   },
   "answer": "He may prosecute his personal case in Court",
   "reason": "See; Sec. 36(6)(c), CFRN."
  },
  {
   "id": "31",
   "question": "Lawyers are enjoined to have offices where they practice and can receive instructions from clients so as not to breach what Rule of RPC?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Rule 20",
    "b": "Rule 21",
    "c": "Rule 22",
    "d": "Rule 23"
   },
   "answer": "Rule 22",
   "reason": "Rule 22 prevents calling at a client house or place of business for the purpose of taking instructions except in exceptional cases like ill health, extreme old age etc."
  },
  {
   "id": "32",
   "question": "Payment of Practice fee is covered by what Rule?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Rule 9",
    "b": "Rule 8",
    "c": "Rule 10",
    "d": "Rule 7"
   },
   "answer": "Rule 9",
   "reason": "Failure to pay practice fee will deprive the lawyer of right to audience in court and other things see Rule 9 RPC"
  },
  {
   "id": "33",
   "question": "It is not unethical for a legal practitioner to:",
   "options": {
    "a": "Stand surety for a respectable client",
    "b": "Reveal confidential information after the termination of the client-counsel relationship.",
    "c": "Thoroughly investigate facts communicated by his client",
    "d": "Accept an instruction which involves arguing against the interest of a party paying his retainer"
   },
   "answer": "Thoroughly investigate facts communicated by his client",
   "reason": "A legal practitioner is enjoined to investigate facts presented by his clients. Rule 25, RPC."
  },
  {
   "id": "34",
   "question": "Generally, legal practitioners ought to pay their practicing fees on or before when?",
   "options": {
    "a": "January 31st",
    "b": "March 31st",
    "c": "August 31st",
    "d": "December 31st"
   },
   "answer": "March 31st",
   "reason": "Practicing fee should be paid not later than 31st March every year. see Rule 9 RPC"
  },
  {
   "id": "35",
   "question": "Who appoints the Chairman of the Council of Legal Education",
   "options": {
    "a": "The Attorney General of the Federation",
    "b": "The Chief Justice of Nigeria",
    "c": "The President of Nigeria",
    "d": "The National Judicial Council"
   },
   "answer": "The President of Nigeria",
   "reason": "The chairman is appointed by the President on the recommendation of the AGF"
  },
  {
   "id": "36",
   "question": "Which of these is not a dereliction of duty to the profession by counsel?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Instigating litigation directly or indirectly.",
    "b": "Searching of land titles for defects.",
    "c": "Counselling agents and other persons to follow up on accidents with intention to have employment.",
    "d": "Giving of proper advice to those seeking relief against unfaithful and neglectful counsel."
   },
   "answer": "Giving of proper advice to those seeking relief against unfaithful and neglectful counsel.",
   "reason": "See; Rule 47, RPC."
  },
  {
   "id": "37",
   "question": "In announcing appearance in court, the expression “your Honour” is used before one of the following courts.___",
   "options": {
    "a": "Magistrate Court in Lagos State",
    "b": "High court in Asaba, Delta State",
    "c": "Area court in Gusau, Zamfara State",
    "d": "Magistrate Court in Enugu, Enugu State."
   },
   "answer": "Magistrate Court in Lagos State",
   "reason": "Your Honour is used to address Magistrates in Lagos State while in other states, they use Your Worship"
  },
  {
   "id": "38",
   "question": "Where a counsel knows that he would most likely be called as a witness in a case, then he should:",
   "options": {
    "a": "Accept the brief because cab rank rule admits no exception",
    "b": "Transfer the case to another person in his firm to handle.",
    "c": "Accept the brief, as that does not bar Him from testifying in the case",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "None of the above",
   "reason": "Rule 20, RPC. Where a counsel knows that he would most likely be called as a witness in a case, then he should not accept the brief. This applies to the firm."
  },
  {
   "id": "39",
   "question": "A lawyer shall not wear the Barrister or Senior Advocate robe in all of the following circumstances except:",
   "options": {
    "a": "As directed by the Bar Council",
    "b": "When conducting his own case as party to a legal proceeding in Court.",
    "c": "When giving evidence in a legal Proceeding in Court",
    "d": "d.When attending a procession in his church where they want to recognise him."
   },
   "answer": "As directed by the Bar Council",
   "reason": "Rule 45 RPC"
  },
  {
   "id": "40",
   "question": "A legal practitioner may be disciplined in respect of all the following except:",
   "options": {
    "a": "Infamous conduct in a professional respect",
    "b": "Conviction by any court anywhere",
    "c": "Obtaining enrolment by fraud",
    "d": "Conducts which are incompatible with the status of a legal practitioner."
   },
   "answer": "Conviction by any court anywhere",
   "reason": "The reason is because the conviction has to be by a court having power to award imprisonment in Nigeria. Sec. 11(1)(b), LPA."
  }
 ]}
